[Music]
though Sheen your interview the
interview that we put out earlier in the
summer called a Zen master talks about
Jordan Peterson in the shadow has become
one of the most viewed things on our
channel certainly the most viewed thing
that doesn't actually have Jordan
Pederson in it and some really
interesting really polarized reactions
so I'd love to explore that with you now
kind of why it was so successful and
also why people seem to either love it
or hate it
you're a Zen master we are back once
again with the renegade master I think
of myself more as a troublemaker
renegade work so we were just speaking
before and you said that it has already
kind of affected your life in a way well
it has certainly increased the number of
people subscribing to our YouTube
channel exponentially I might add so
that's interesting we've had to create a
little more content the polarization
that happened on the interview was very
interesting to me and I'd like to talk
about it a little because I think it's a
it's informative there's so much that
can be learned from polarization when I
read the comments I noticed just a rough
glance about 40% of them thought I I was
I sucked and about 40% of them thought I
walked on water and about 20% of them
thought I was just weird so to me I
really pay attention to what Byron Katie
says it's congruent with my experience
she says we don't talk to each other we
talked to each other's projections but
only 98% of the time so what I saw was
all of that that I was reading were
projections they were projections of
shadows some golden shadows and some
ugly shadows but for me personally it
was a gold mine because I know that even
though their shadows and I shouldn't
take it literally every time somebody
projects something on me there's a hook
inside me that that projection can hang
on so it was a gold mine in the sense
that those those those comments were
mirrors that enabled me to see some
things about myself that were
fascinating so I want to thank you for
that say more about what were those
things well I I did notice that the one
of the things that really upset some
people not all everyone and again half
the people that delighted half the
people it it troubled them was my
laughter and to me that is just it's a
practice that we consciously do we call
it sacred laughter I had a quick look
back through the comments just before
this interview and one of the things
that a lot of people seem to talk about
was they found parts of maybe the laughs
we've already talked about but
inauthentic fake or inauthentic what do
you what do you make of that you know
that that fascinated me if you talked to
any of my students and you asked them
what is the most important thing that
they're here you know what they say and
you can ask these two if you like it's
my authenticity my integrity so that one
really it really puzzled me I didn't see
their there must be something in the way
that I'm using emotions because I'm
playing with emotions you know the
we create emotions I mean actors create
emotions for an impact and I know that
that's something that I consciously do I
must not do it very well as all I could
think of because alle my colleague was
talking about the woods and he was
saying how perfect the reaction was
because the art of of R in zazen is the
trickster archetype it's the renegade
archetype so the fact that it was so
polarizing the fact that people have
such a mixed reaction to it was in some
sense a perfectly Zen reaction to the
interview and that is conscious that is
a conscious intention that I am
deliberately doing the the the biggest
thing I want to accomplish is I want you
to be uncomfortable because that's where
you're gonna grow safety is the most
unsafe spiritual path you can take it
leaves you frozen in fear unable to take
risks unable to learn and grow and that
is something I deliberately
intentionally do you can ask anybody in
the Sangha that as well this is part of
integrals in you know if you're not
willing to be uncomfortable you're in
the wrong Sangha go find another one and
we tell you that right up front
something came up when you were talking
about the reading the comments and it's
quite exposing like putting stuff out
there and then reading what people think
of it what I hear you saying about this
is extremely valuable information it's
really valuable to have all of these
people sort of reflecting back what
they're saying
yes it's valuable to reflect on that and
in internally look at where the hooks
are so the laughter was one example the
collective shadows were another example
you know I happen to think a whole lot
of Jordan Peterson I think he's an
amazing guy he's brilliant and I was
fascinated just because I was
criticizing one little thing people
projected a devil on me that was
fascinating that's a collective shadow
that's if you don't agree with me I'm
going to attack you it's not a very high
level
collective shadow it it is so important
in integrals in to let everything inform
you we let the body inform us we let the
nature inform us we let dreams inform us
we let our emotions inform us we let our
thoughts inform us we let our
projections and other people's
projections inform us why would you turn
away a teacher everyone is my teacher
why would I rob myself of these
teachings and this is something that I
think a lot of people don't realize
about spirituality or true spirituality
which is it's not supposed to be a
palliative it should make you question
like true spirituality is is designed to
make you uncomfortable it's designed to
make your ego uncomfortable to allow
something else to emerge yes yes the the
ego wants to be safe the ego wants to be
comfortable and it's not a bad thing
this is why we're here we survived but
it it is antagonistic to developing
insight and spiritual growth and it's
it's antagonistic to seeing your shadows
because shadow work by definition is
uncomfortable your your seeing the parts
of yourself that you've repressed you're
dealing with emotions that you've
suppressed and it is guaranteed to be
uncomfortable and true religious
breakthroughs are the same way the
insights so by definition by training
it's my job to make people uncomfortable
where does that become dangerous though
because I think a lot of people rate
question I think a lot of people are
very suspicious of spirituality because
we've we've seen many spiritual
communities go bad and while they're
going bad a lot of the spiritual
teachers are saying no it's just people
can't handle how crazy wise I am or how
how I'm I don't follow your petty ball
to our rules like this this can be very
difficult how do we know when things are
getting out of control and people are
getting hurt this is so important in
Bryn's eyes in the the Roshi
the Zen master has absolute authority
now this is problematic if a Renzi Zen
master goes crazy
he's got absolute authority he's got
absolute power and he's he's the only
one that's really this is a serious
problem and you you see this problem
happening all over spiritual communities
you see it with my beloved so Gil
Rinpoche the Tibetan Book of the Dead
fell out of favor with his students my
teachers teacher IDO Shimano had a real
problem with this this is a real common
thing where these Eastern teachers come
to the West it's like they don't have
the antibodies for the Western viruses
that cultural viruses that they're
succumbed to so what we've done in
integrals in consciously the Board of
Directors can fire me if I get out of
hand we have an integrity circle that
can challenge me and if if you were to
form a complaint about me
it would go to the integrity circle and
they would evaluate it and they would
determine whether there's a real problem
and they would intervene and they have
my ear and they have my total commitment
to follow their advice if they say I
need therapy because I'm in shadow and
I'm projecting that shadow onto you they
have the authority to hold my feet to
the fire and if I if I don't succumb
they go to the board of directors and
they fire me it's in our bylaws and it's
consciously put there to compensate for
exactly this problem but it's absolutely
in in essential we want the most
awakened person in
charge at least able to have veto power
to keep us from doing something stupid
as an organization so we're not willing
to give that up but we have to have some
checks and balances to compensate for my
shadows and we have that well in place
in this saga at what point does
unsettling someone and playing with the
ego become dangerous it can go wrong
like it almost it almost seems spiritual
communities almost go bad as many times
as they go well it seems
how do people avoid that generally I
don't think you do I think you you need
to compensate for that institutionally
the integrity circle in integrals in
which is some of our most senior
students their job is to protect other
students from my shadows and and their
job is also to protect me from
collective shadows of the students and
individual this is a really important
mechanism that we need to have real good
psychotherapy and shadow work and people
that are practicing at a high level of
spirituality we need that to be in place
to avoid that exact scenario and if you
join an organization and you find that
isn't in place make note take heed
because it will go badly especially with
someone who say and they have no I've
heard that from spiritual teachers as
well
I have no shadows you won't hear it from
me what do you if someone says to you I
have no shadows do you run a mile should
you run a mile no I don't run but I
challenge the shit out of them
I laugh in their face and I'll challenge
them because if as Roger Walsh said
brilliantly I don't care who you are
spiritual teacher president of the
United States
everybody has shadows
surely not the president the United
States surely not that's the British oh
my god does he have shadows
surely not brexit right so I think this
is really an important thing to discuss
and it applies not just to spiritual
teachers it applies to workship shop
leaders you know you you when you're
doing rebel wisdom workshops you need to
have the same kind of mechanisms in
place and if you don't it's you need to
get some yeah and I'll be happy to help
you with that we've learned we'd made
lots of mistakes in coming to the place
where we have and what I always ask is
not do you have shadows that's a given
do you know what your shadows are that's
a more pertinent question and if you
can't answer that question and tell me
what your shadows are then I walk away
mmm that's actually the very first
whenever we do any collaborative project
that's the first process that we do is
going round and we use the format if you
worked with me you would learn and then
you would learn that I don't take advice
very well I always think I'm right that
and that is the oh that is invariably
the thing that deepens the field and if
you don't I think if you don't do that
then you're whatever organisation or
whatever collaboration you're doing is
going to have unspoken stuff under the
surface that's going to take you down at
some point so it feels like a process
that needs to happen I bow to that mmm
yeah that's beautiful
thanks I'm happy to hear that I
suspected as much just getting to seeing
the twinkle in your eye when we talk
about shadows and spirituality yeah yeah
I I think shadow work is the what's
really interesting I think shadow work
is the key work for right now but also
there's a real upsurge of interest in it
as well this is something that we've
seen in our workshops people are now
coming with a concept of the shadow
which they would probably not have had
even quite recently which I think partly
that could be Jordan Pederson
popularizing the union idea of the
shadow but just generally
does feel like the time of the
integration of the shadow yeah he
certainly had an impact on that there's
no question about it and I'm just
delighted to see that shadows are
something that I have been studying for
quite a while in fact a lot of my
students affectionately call me and some
not so affectionately the shadow Roshi
and I I'm not sure if it's because I do
so much work with shadows or I have so
many shadows maybe a combination I will
have to ask them could you give a
concrete example of what this is
something that we're often people often
ask us how do you work on the shadow we
talk about the shadow a lot can you give
a practical example of how to work on
the shadow yes so one of the surefire
ways and I've heard you talk about this
especially when you were talking about
the interview and people's comments when
you two were talking if something
bothers you about somebody like let's
take Trump for example Trump bothers me
because he's so arrogant and he's so
contracted and unwilling he just attacks
when anybody criticizes he attacks them
now if that bothers me and you see my
energy coming up my emotion which is I'm
acting right now because it really
doesn't bother me because I've seen that
shadow in myself
I'm manufacturing that emotion for
effect so some people will probably say
that's inauthentic and it'll bother them
and what does that tell us but they're
inauthentic
exactly exactly but if it bothered me
that Trump was attacking every time he
was criticized then that would be an
automatic indication that I'm being
defensive and that's exactly what I
and that would be an example of me
projecting my shadow onto him now he has
a hook that my projection will fall on
because he is like that
he's extremely attacking ruthlessly
attacking when anybody criticizes him
he's hypersensitive to it so there's a
hook this big dang my projection on him
but if I'd look at him and I just see
it's factual you know he's just like
that and I can't believe that he's
President of the United States and I
really see the harm that that causes
everywhere I look but it doesn't bother
me with that level of personalized
emotion now it bothers me because I'm an
American and it's embarrassing you know
for the rest of the world but I mean
that's just showing the American shadow
you Britt surely can see that pretty
clearly Trump is a great example because
on some level he is holding a projection
and also the sense is for me at least
that he is the perfect trigger for the
liberal projections the liberal shadow
but my concern is that at the moment the
necessary self-examination that Trump
has won the election the liberal
worldview has been decisively rejected
or rejected in the in the election by a
lot of people who don't share it there
is not there's not a lot of
self-reflection going on from what I see
in liberal America there's none they are
in shadow and they need to do some
shadow work you know the the book that
Wilbur wrote on Trump really articulates
that clearly it just nails that the the
fact that the Liberals can't see how
much Trump bothers them is even scarier
than Trump to me the
that that whole thing is in shadow and
disowned makes them more dangerous than
Trump more dangerous only because
they're more evolved and what they're in
shadow with is hidden they're much more
skillful at hiding their shadow than
Trump is he can't hide his shadow it's
blatantly obvious which makes it less
dangerous to me so what is the shadow
that's hidden and that's context
Erica's liberal arrogance liberal
arrogance and passive-aggressive
violence that's been repressed it's it's
it's so likely to explode out I mean we
we last interview we talked about
culture wars that's two shadows
conflicting right if if you and I were
in that position where we polarized to
the point that the liberals and
conservatives had then we would be that
far from coming to blows this is gonna
explode in a very ugly way I don't see
anything to make it better I don't see
anything happening to stop the deadlock
and that's frightening that's really
frightening I think I agree because the
idea of even a mediator between the two
sides just seems like a non-starter at
the moment like I don't see that was
going to be one of my questions
is there a way for America to pull out
of the sort of spiral of polarization
that it's in at the moment I don't see
it
short of a disaster so what do you say
you asked me that question before you
can ask it again
I see disaster that's what I see and I
don't see a specific disaster I don't
prophesies anything but I see the only
thing that's going to shock us out of
this culture war that we're in is
something so severe
that it creates a problem that's bigger
than the one we're projecting on each
other that's the only thing that I mean
we're gonna have to have a bigger enemy
than each other to unite us into a new
war against a common enemy that's how
nature solves such problems called war
and if you look at the world situation
the center cannot hold that William
Butler Yeats poem the second coming the
best lack all conviction and the worst
are full of passionate intensity that's
what I see happening what's gonna happen
don't know I'm not a prophet but I
really see where polarization leads us
I see where it led us in the 30s into
the Second World War there Shane thank
you again yes it's always a pleasure
David I I want to just really appreciate
what you're doing and particularly
because you're tackling the rough
problems and questions that nobody else
wants to tackle and the the brave effort
that you're putting into this and
putting it all out there on the line oh
yeah oh yeah that's a Zen thing isn't it
way it's an integral set thing right
what are my brilliant students brought
that in and they did great don't doesn't
it feel good oh yeah
it's like blowing shit up hey Shane
thank you deepest gratitude
anytime I'm so delighted that shadow
work is becoming popular because it's
absolutely essential our survival may
depend upon this work
[Music]
you